Guide to the 3:16 Bible Texts Illuminated
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
3:16 Bible Texts Illuminated
1978-1996
1985-1996
SC0399
Knuth, Donald Ervin, 1938-
5.75 Linear feet and 340 megabytes
Collection includes Knuth's research notes, drafts of the manuscript and readers' comments, correspondence with Hermann Zapf, artistic co-worker, correspondence with illustrators and publishers, artwork, proofs, and "exabyte" computer tapes of the artwork, text, and fonts used in the book. Also included is correspondence, exhibit texts and records, photographs, ephemera, financial records, and clippings, 1991-1996, pertaining to the traveling exhibit of artwork from the book, designed and organized by Jennifer S. Knuth.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Donald E. Knuth, 1991 and 1996.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Professor of computer science at Stanford University.
Description of the Collection
Collection includes Knuth's research notes, drafts of the manuscript and readers' comments, correspondence with Hermann Zapf, artistic co-worker, correspondence with illustrators and publishers, artwork, proofs, and "exabyte" computer tapes of the artwork, text, and fonts used in the book. Also included is correspondence, exhibit texts and records, photographs, ephemera, financial records, and clippings, 1991-1996, pertaining to the traveling exhibit of artwork from the book, designed and organized by Jennifer S. Knuth.
Access Terms
Knuth, Donald Ervin, 1938-; Knuth, Jennifer S.; Stanford University. Computer Science Department. Faculty.; Zapf, Hermann; Bible--Commentaries.; Bible--Study.; Calligraphy.; Illustrations.; Museum exhibits.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - First computer output of Old Testament portion., March 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - First computer output of New Testament portion., March 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Comments by Rev. Norman Pfotenhauer and Rev. Jon Dechow. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Comments by Rev. Robert Nicholus. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Comments by Richard Stout. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Comments by Joyce Tirbak. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Comments by David Shewmake, Tom Leep. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Comments by Guy Steele Jr, Ken Rietz, Dan McCracken. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Comments by R.F. Gray, R.W. Howell, R. Gundry. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Comments, miscellaneous. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Comments by Shannon Moffat. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Comments by Tim Enos. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Comments by Jill Knuth. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Master copy for final editing, February-April 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Index preparation, May 1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Xeroxes of calligraphy (working index to illustrations), 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - CORRESPONDENCE WITH CALLIGRAPHERS
    - Genesis 3:16, Exodus 3:16.
      - Van Dijk, Evert (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Williams, Robert (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Leviticus 3:16, Numbers 3:16.
      - David, Ismar (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Ruuhinen, Erkki (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Deuteronomy 3:16, Joshua 3:16.
      - Larcher, Jean (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Shepherd, Margaret (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Judges 3:16, Ruth 3:16.
      - Borja, Robert (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Veljovic, Jovica (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1 Samuel 3:16, 2 Samuel 3:16.
      - Wadisherla, S. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Waters, Julian (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1 Kings 3:16, 2 Kings 3:16.
      - Bongard, Hermann (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Kot, Andrzej (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1 Chronicles 3:16, 2 Chronicles 3:16.
      - Bongard, Hermann (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Wong, Allen Q. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Ezra 4:3, Nehemiah 3:16.
      - Hechle, Ann (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Pao, Derick (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Esther 4:1, Job 3:16.
      - Eberhardt, Fritz (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Maletto, Luigi Cesare (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Psalm 4:8, Proverbs 3:16.
      - Holmes, Kris (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Taylor, Susie (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Ecclesiastes 3:16, Song of Solomon 4:5.
      - Rohde, Bent (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Waters, Sheila (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Isaiah 3:16, Jeremiah 3:16.
      - Dieterich, Claude (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Jackson, Donald (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Lamentations 3:16, Ezekiel 3:16.
      - Deaver, Georgia (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Harvey, Michael (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Daniel 3:16, Hosea 4:11.
      - Horlbeck-Kappler, Irmgard (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Skaggs, Steven (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Stone, Sumner (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Joel 3:16, Amos 4:1.
      - Fraterdeus, Peter (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Peter, Fred (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Jonah 4:6, Micah 4:4.
      - Girvin, Timothy S. (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Wronker, Lili Cassel (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Nahum 3:16, Habakkuk 3:16.
      - Briem, Gunnlaugur SE (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Hoefer, Karlgeorg (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Zephaniah 3:16, Zechariah 4:6.
      - Jones, Pam (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Mediavilla, Claude (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Malachi 3:16, Matthew 3:16.
      - Maveety, Darle (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Neugebauer, Friedrich (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Mark 3:16, Luke 3:16.
      - Bernd, Adolf (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Koeth, Alice (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - John 3:16, Acts 3:16.
      - Hoffman, Lothar (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Zapf, Herman (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Romans 3:16, 1 Corinthians 3:16.
      - Linz, Alfred (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Toots, Villu (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 2 Corinthians 3:16, Galatians 3:16.
      - Kratky, Luboimir (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Zigany, Edit (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Ephesians 3:16, Philippians 3:16.
      - Anckers, Kerstin (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Rodriguez-Benitez, Guillermo (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Colossians 3:16, 1 Thessalonians 4:3.
      - Billawala, Nazneen N. (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Snape, Margaret (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - 2 Thessalonians 3:16, 1 Timothy 3:16.
      - Pronenko, Leonid (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Zapf-von Hesse, Gudrun (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - 2 Timothy 3:16, Hebrews 3:16.
      - Kindersley, David (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Stevens, John (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - James 3:16, 1 Peter 3:16.
      - Kelly, Jerry (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Mendoza y Almeida, Jose (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 2 Peter 3:16, 1 John 3:16.
      - Evans, Jean (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Wong, Jeanyee (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Revelation 3:16.
      - Cusick, Rick (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Letters from Knuth to calligraphers and readers. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Knuth received just after publication. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence with Hermann Zapf. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Calligraphers who declined. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with publishers (unsuccessful). (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with A-R Editions. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Permission forms signed by artists. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Original MS notes for Bible class given in 1978. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous working papers, Boston, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Invitation to calligraphers, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - ORIGINAL MS NOTES FOR BOOK, 1985-1989
    - Front matter. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Genesis 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Exodus 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Leviticus 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Numbers 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Deuteronomy 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Joshua 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Judges 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Ruth 3:16 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - 1 Samuel 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 2 Samuel 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - 1 Kings 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - 2 Kings 3:16. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - 1 Chronicles 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 2 Chronicles 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Ezra 4:3. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Nehemiah 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Esther 4:1. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Job 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Psalm 4:8. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Proverbs 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Ecclesiastes 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Song of Solomon 4:5. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Isaiah 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Jeremiah 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Lamentations 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Ezekiel 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Daniel 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Hosea 4:11. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Joel 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Amos 4:1. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Jonah 4:6. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Micah 4:4. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Nahum 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Habakkuk 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Zephaniah 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Zechariah 4:6. (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Malachi 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Matthew 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Mark 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Luke 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - John 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Acts 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Romans 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - 1 Corinthians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - 2 Corinthians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Galatians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Ephesians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Philippians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Colossians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - 1 Thessalonians 4:3. (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - 2 Thessalonians 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - 1 Timothy 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - 2 Timothy 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Hebrews 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - James 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - 1 Peter 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - 2 Peter 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - 1 John 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Revelations 3:16. (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Rear matter. (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Laserprinted reference set of illustration plates. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Special reprints of illustration pages. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Dummy book." (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Unbound signatures. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Notebook from experiments at Adobe Systems, Inc. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Computer files--printouts. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photographic plates (spares). (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - COMPUTER TAPES (Box 7)
    These are so-called "exabyte tapes," containing millions of bytes of "precious data" although they are very small. The first two tapes were made at Adobe Systems in 1989; they contain information from artwork as originally scanned into digital form before editing.
    The third tape contains files in the PostScript language that will generate all 139 plates of illustrations used in the book. It also contains files in the TeX language that will generate the complete text, and files in the METAFONT language that will produce the special fonts used. It also contains records of correspondence with the artists and the labels used in a traveling exhibit of calligraphy constructed from the artwork for this book.
  - Zapf, Hermann - correspondence with D. Knuth and others, 1984-85 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Zapf, Hermann - correspondence with D. Knuth and others, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Zapf, Hermann - correspondence with D. Knuth and others, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Zapf, Hermann - correspondence with D. Knuth and others, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Zapf, Hermann - correspondence with D. Knuth and others, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Zapf, Hermann - correspondence with D. Knuth and others, 1990-91 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - FLAT ART I (ledger size): (Box 1 os)
    Contains various sketches and layouts by the artists, and also includes original art work by Veljovic', Wadisherla, Kot, Schneider, Jackson, Peter, Hoefer, Bernd, Zapf, Zigany.
  - FLAT ART II (map size): (Box 1 mc)
    Contains the following, from bottom to top:
    - Plates from sample chapter printed at Nimrod Press, Boston, 1986. (Folder 1)
    - Plates from exhibition brochure printed at Slonaker's, Palo Alto, 1989. (Folder 2)
    - Hermann Zapf's original layout for the poster, January 1990. (Folder 3)
    - Proofs of the poster, Singapore, October-November 1990. (Folder 4)
    - Example of the final poster. (Folder 5)
    - Signatures printed on illustration side only. (Folder 6)
    - Sample covers at press time, showing significant color variation. (Folder 7)
    - Sample signatures at press time, showing significant color variation. (Folder 8)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-1996-146
  This addition to the collection pertains to the traveling exhibit of artwork from the book, designed and organized by Jennifer S. Knuth. Included are correspondence, exhibit texts and records, photographs, ephemera, financial records, and clippings. There are also some financial records and other materials pertaining to the production of the book.
  - "Exploring 3:16," a study guide by Rev. Robert Nicholus (Box 1)
  - Proofs for the publisher's brochure about the book (Box 1)
  - Changes to be made in the second printing (Box 1)
  - Canceled checks [includes many calligraphers' autographs] (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with calligraphers, 1991-1996 [Neugebauer, Briem, Kot, Zapf, Wronker] (Box 1)
  - Financial records for 3:16 book and exhibit [includes correspondence with customs officials re international transport] (Box 1)
  - Mat board for the exhibit (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's first workbook for exhibit design and organization (Box 1)
  - Printing of stationery and brochures about the exhibit (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's correspondence with artists (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's drafts for exhibit labels, edited by D. Knuth and S. Taylor (Box 1)
  - Exhibit labels as they are taking shape (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's drafts for exhibit panels (Box 1)
  - Complete set of 35mm slides of the 73 frames in the exhibit (Box 1)
  - Booklet containing texts of the exhibit panels and labels; and German translation of that booklet (Box 1)
  - Photos of the exhibit in Penticton, 100 computer file(s) (TIFF)
  - National Endowment for the Arts: application, correspondence, final report (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's drafts for brochure and cover litter to potential exhibitors (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's second workbook for exhibit coordination (Box 1)
  - Jennifer's third workbook for exhibit coordination (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous press clippings, posters, and reviews from exhibit sites [from Stanford to Washington to Bratislava, Slovakia] (Box 1)
  - Info packet for potential exhibitors; final list of exhibit sites; addresses (Box 1)
  - Letters from calligraphers donating their work to the San Francisco Library (Box 1)
  - Condition Record Book of the exhibit - detailed notes on each piece from each exhibit site (Box 1)
  - Copy of Tim Girvin's artwork (Box 1)